Awesome. Welcome back to our fifth and
final day of the Kaggle Generative AI
Intensive course sponsored by Google and
featuring many of the great products
that we have in our ML developer team
including the Gemini APIs, AI Studio,
and a lot more across Google Cloud. We
have been so excited to see the interest
from all of you over the course of the
last 5 days
as you learned about foundation models,
prompting foundation models, vector
databases, embeddings, fine-tuning
models, agents, and today our fifth and
final day how you actually put these
systems into production and maintain
them over time.
I have heard that there have been
so many folks stress testing our
infrastructure that there might have
been some issues with latency both in
terms of the APIs as well as
with our fine-tuning features. So if
you've been experiencing any delays with
fine-tuning, never fear.
This is just due to the large number of
folks who have enrolled in the course
pinging the services at the same time.
So if you do run into delays today, make
sure to try out, you know, next week or
or perhaps a little bit later. We should
have those wrinkles ironed out. So thank
you again for attending. It has meant
the world to all of the organizers, the
authors of the white papers,
the people creating the code labs and
more,
and we're really excited to have this
final session for you today where we'll
be discussing ML Ops for Generative AI.
So welcome.
As I mentioned before, my name is Paige.
I work on our ML developer team helping
support things like Colab, Gemini APIs,
AI Studio, Kaggle, and more,
and I'm overjoyed today
to get to to share some of the code labs
that the teams have been working on as
well as to welcome our expert hosts to
answer all of your great questions from
the Discord.
So with that, just as a reminder, this
is the fifth and final day of our
Generative AI Intensive course. Each day
you have daily assignments including
white paper readings, podcasts that you
can listen to that are overviews of the
white paper, some code labs that are
intended for you to walk through them to
kind of learn in a hands-on capacity how
to use all of the great products that we
mentioned,
a Discord channel to discuss and to ask
questions and to engage with our course
instructors,
and then also some really interesting
kind of daily videos
like today where we will walk through
walk through your questions and and kind
of give voice overs to some of that
great content. This is sponsored by
Kaggle
and has been a beautiful collaboration
between the Kaggle team, Gemini APIs,
and also many other teams throughout
Alphabet including our Vertex AI and
Cloud AI teams who are represented here
today.
And again, this is our fifth and final
day
covering ML Ops and Generative AI. Today
we will be first
kind of going through the code labs in
the curriculum review, so the white
papers and the podcasts that hopefully
you listened to. Then we'll be doing a
Q&A all about ML Ops with Generative AI,
and then finally we'll be walking
through a pop quiz where you'll be
testing out all of the things that you
learned, and hopefully hopefully
kind of getting some insights into
things that might be a little bit tricky
or easy to miss in the white paper. So I
hope you pay attention. Make sure to pay
attention in the Q&A as well. And with
that, I'm going to turn it over to Anat
and to Ilya who are going to be walking
through the curriculum review
and also our code review. So Anat, Ilya,
do you want to
take it away?
Thank you, Paige. So I'll begin with the
curriculum overview and hand it over to
Ilya for the code overview. So welcome
everyone, and just a heads-up as Paige
mentioned for those of you who are
encountering some delays in the
in the day four code lab, we've also
made and shared a bonus code lab for
you. So until until there is less people
tuning in the same time, you can try out
our bonus code lab shared on Discord and
we share it further as well.
Great. So moving on to giving you a
curriculum overview of what we discussed
so far. So a brief recap on day one, we
discussed foundation models, how they
created, tuned, prompt engineering, how
they can be prompted to achieve task
optimal outcomes. Then on day two, we
moved on to
topic of embeddings and vector stores to
see how data can be represented of
various different data types in compact
semantic representations
which can be queried and managed at
scale using techniques like vector
search in vector databases, and how
these two can be combined together with
more advanced prompt techniques in day
three
together with
techniques like AI function calling,
etc. to build complex
agents, generative AI agents which can
call upon various
databases, vectors databases, etc. to
solve tasks tasks which
complex in nature and require various
different tapping into various different
data sources and techniques. And and
building on from the first two three
days in day four yesterday, you saw
the topic of domain specific LLMs like
Med LLM, Sec LLMs which talked about how
they utilize the techniques like RAG,
agents, and prompt engineering
to and more to build domain specific
models specialized for cybersecurity and
healthcare. And today
we'll be discussing a topic of
building all the models and databases
and techniques of putting it all
together in a production ready system so
that you can actually take all of these
great techniques, models, methods, and
actually make use of it in a production
environment and all the consideration
that needs to be taken for that. So and
hopefully you had a
moment to look at the white paper, and
and I'll just give you a brief overview
of the white paper. So in the white
paper you that you read, you we
discussed a few core concepts. We
discussed of how
Sorry. We'll be bringing
how to bring Generative AI
projects from prototypes to production
focusing focusing on using ML Ops on
on Vertex AI. And it started off by
focusing on things like discovery and
basically how do you effectively select
the correct foundational model from the
many options available with different
strengths and weaknesses and tradeoffs
that we have to consider including
performance, cost, and more. Then we
moved on to the to the next section
which was around developing, evaluating,
and experimenting with these models
which focuses on iterative development
and basically rigorous evaluation of
end-to-end generative AI applications.
In here we also established a robust
framework for evaluating
these these
generative AI applications and
end-to-end applications of these models
including task and business specific
metrics
using various evaluation methods which
we'll be discussing later on as well
like side-by-side evaluation and more.
And we also then looked at how
development of in the development phase
we use various techniques that we
discussed in the previous days such as
prompt engineering, RAG, agent-based
systems,
and and integrate all of these
techniques together in
in a package for which allows robust
experiment tracking, versioning,
evaluation, and more to allow allow
developers who build these systems to
iterate reliably.
The next section after that we looked at
deployment, and deployment covers
kind of takes a page from DevOps and
extends it to Generative AI and covers
basically the deployment aspects of
Generative AI which also includes
continuous integration, continuous
delivery, and
but like tailored to specific challenges
of large language models and multimodal
models as well.
After that, we looked at one very
important metric that was also
applicable to deployment of
predictive models but
especially complex when it comes when
applied to large language models which
includes monitoring and logging. So
things like drift detection when the
prompts drift away or prompts or the
outputs drift away from the intended
distribution as well as
continuous evaluation to make sure that
the application that you are building is
is performing as as it's supposed to in
production. And finally, in the last
part we looked at governance. Basically,
it's a cross-cutting practice that
refers to all the activities that aim
that establishing control,
accountability, and transparency over
the development and deployment process.
Now,
now that you've looked at various stages
of what's considered what should be
considered in ML Ops, let's now shift
over to a practical demonstration using
an end-to-end starter pack for
Generative AI showcasing how it
simplifies building and deploying
Generative AI applications on Google
Cloud. So you've gotten the link for
that in the email.
If not, please check your email and
hopefully you've had time to go through
it, but I'll hand it over to my
colleague Ilya for going and going
through the demo. Ilya, off to you.
Thanks a lot, Anat.
So as part of this
part, I'm going to share my screen.
So I will explain a little bit about the
background of the starter pack which is
essentially a resource you can use
for reducing time to production and
seeing an example on how you can build
production ready Generative AI
applications and implementing practice
some of the techniques we mentioned on
the white paper.
Why we are creating this starter pack?
So, we are creating it because we
realize
that um
uh prototyping is typically
uh
easy part when it comes to building
GenAI application. However, the last
mile, the part that will you will
require to get to production is actually
a really tricky one. And so, we noticed
there are some existing challenges
uh in bringing GenAI applications to
production. One of them is the
deployment and operational parts, which
is how you build your infrastructure,
how you perform testing, how you perform
deployment, how you build an UI.
Then you have the evaluation part, which
Ananth just mentioned. How you perform
How you measure performance, how you
build synthetic data.
Then we have the customization part,
which is how do you integrate customer
logic and how do you implement security
and compliance. And finally, the
observability. So, how you collect data
to make sure then you can use it for
tuning purposes or evaluation purposes,
how you do How you monitor the service
and how you monitor user feedback. So,
we noticed there are these challenges
here and so, we created a starter pack
as a way to democratize some of the
solutions for this. So, the starter pack
essentially will offer a
production-ready FastAPI server, which
will allow you to do a real-time chat
interface, event streaming, and auto
generation of docs.
Uh it will include a UI playground for
experimentation purposes.
It will include a whole the CICD and
Terraform you will need to perform a
quick deployment.
Then it will offer different patterns,
uh so like different ways to build
agents or rag applications. And finally,
it will showcase how you can achieve
observability. So, essentially allowing
you to track everything that the user is
doing with the application.
So, we can directly go to uh code with
through an alive demo. Um as Ananth
mentioned, there is a link you should
have received in case you want to
simulate what I'm doing on my side as
well.
Okay. Um and
essentially, like if we want to start If
you want to start using the starter
pack, you will land into the main folder
here, which is under our generative AI
official Google Cloud repo.
Uh and it's under Gemini sample apps
end-to-end GenAI app starter pack.
To use it, you will need to
um you will need to essentially download
a zip file we offer here.
Uh and then of course, install
dependencies. Um
Essentially, we implement an
architecture which use different
components of Google Cloud from Cloud
Run to Vertex AI Model Garden, Vertex AI
Evaluation, BigQuery, and so on.
Let's jump into my IDE now, where I will
be able to show you an example of that.
And as part of the starter pack,
we also offer um
a series of um
a series of
um
a walk-through that you can do to
essentially
um
learn the starter pack in a self-paced
manner.
So,
um
I'm going to essentially for for just
testing a
uh the dummy application we offer as
part of the as part of the starter pack,
I'm going to
run a playground. So, essentially, this
is a Streamlit UI that will allow you to
test end-to-end the starter pack. So,
for example, I can ask a question like
this
and and the model, in this case Gemini,
will respond with
a recipe assistant. So, what's behind
the scenes? So, we can actually look at
the code that is powering this
application here.
To do that, essentially, we have an
application folder, which essentially
will contain the server that is powering
this application, yeah? And behind the
scenes, we use a framework like
LangChain to create
the application. In this case, you can
see here, we are creating an application
which is a culinary assistant uh
specializing in providing cooking
recipes.
Of course, this is just the beginning,
right? Because you can change
what's inside your application, you can
do prompt engineering, evaluation, and
so on to achieve your
goal application. We also offer a series
of patterns as mentioned before, like
how to build an agent with LangGraph,
for example, and how to build a custom
rag Q&A application.
Um
Of course, you can always change the You
can also use some of these patterns
here. And then when you're ready to go
to production, you can actually Before
going to production, you will start to
look at evaluation and so, we offer
actually here
some examples about evaluation
that you might want to use.
And finally, there is the deployment
part where essentially, you will use
tools like Terraform or Cloud Build to
deploy the CICD to production. So, um an
example of that will be that
essentially, as a user, I will use Git
to make a commit. And this then commit
will land I can show you right now it
will land into um
into your own Git provider, where you
will be able to approve or not your
commit. This Before approving, the
starter pack will allow you to do things
like unit test and integration test,
which are typical activities you need to
do before you deploy to production. Uh
Once these activities are done, you will
be able to merge into your main branch.
And then before deploying to production,
typically, what you do is that you
perform a series of tests to
test things like is the container being
built? Uh what's the latency of my
container and things like this. So, for
example, here,
the starter pack will allow you to
auto-generate things like
uh minimum latency, maximum latency. It
will provide you a chart of all the
different kind of
throughput per second that you may have.
And then finally, you will be able to
click the deployment to production,
where you will have your final
application in production. Now, we can
even do a test here, where I'm going to
again go back to
go back to the um
to the Visual Studio Code and um
and and run the application in
production. Uh so, if we go here now and
we replace the URL that we have here
with the URL in production, we should be
able to test our endpoint that I
previously deployed to production.
And there you go. So, you have the
application in production. But it's not
it's not the end of the
um the flow because
when you're running things in
production, you want to also make sure
you're collecting the data, right? And
so, the starter pack is achieving that
by making sure everything the user is
sending to the application is being
logged and then is being saved into
BigQuery.
And so that
as part of the starter pack, we also
offer a nice Looker Studio dashboard
that will allow you to do monitoring of
of like the usage of the application.
You will be able to see things like how
many conversation you got, what's the
feedback collected,
a feedback score over time. And for
every conversation, you will be able to
zoom in
and understand
each each specific
data point where the human and the AI
interacted.
And so, this is everything.
Hope
We are always
available for any clarification. Over to
you, Ananth. Uh
Thanks, Ilya. And for those of you
watching, uh just to make it clear, this
is on Vertex AI. We'll be covering that
in the Q&A. What the cool apps so far
that you've been working on is has been
on AI Studio, which is our
developer-focused one. And Vertex AI is
our enterprise platform for enabling
production-grade systems, which we'll be
covering in the Q&A as well. And just to
mention
Ilya mentioned BigQuery, that's one of
the Vertex AI data warehousing solution
where you can store and analyze large
amounts of data along with a lot of more
advanced functionality. We'll be
including the link for both in the
in the description later on. So, cool.
Thanks a lot, Ilya. And Paige, over to
you for the Q&A.
Excellent. I loved that presentation. I
also especially love anytime I can see a
VS Code or VS Code-like
user interface. I think it's a great way
to to be able to keep everything
keep everything visible and to also be
able to to kind of see how all of the
the bits and components that we've been
learning about over the course of the
week fit together. So, really appreciate
it. Thank you so much, Ilya. That was
amazing.
Um
Excellent. Um so now, we are going to go
to the Q&A.
This Q&A session will be all about MLOps
and generative AI. So, really excited to
have here today a group of really
excellent speakers and also have been
overjoyed to see all of the questions
that you've been posting on Discord
about how to maintain these generative
AI systems over time.
Before we start though, I want to give a
quick shout-out and thank you to all of
our wonderful generative AI course
moderators who over the course of the
last 5 days have been answering your
questions on GitHub, on Discourse, on
on Discord, on Kaggle, on our YouTube
videos.
They've been really working around the
clock. The sun never sets on our
generative AI teams at Google. And just
want to say thank you immensely to Pou
Long, Kaz, Mark, Eric, Irwin, Miles, and
Guillaume.
Y'all are amazing. We really appreciate
you.
And please also make sure to emoji thank
them or thank them just just via text
anytime they they do something helpful
or help point y'all in the right
directions.
So, really really appreciate you. Um and
very very honored to introduce our our
expert panel today. Um we have folks um
from Google DeepMind as well as from our
Google Cloud Vertex teams um and our
Cloud AI and industry solutions teams.
Um so broad broad spectrum of experience
across model evaluation um as well as uh
kind of maintenance of systems over
time. Um
Thank you so much for coming today,
Beer, Elia, Olivia, Socrates, Advait,
Gabriella, and of course Anant. Um uh we
have a wonderful kind of collection of
questions to answer today and in the
interest of time I am going to get right
into it. Um so question number one for
Gabriella, how has ML Ops changed with
the introduction of large language
models and generative AI? You know, I
started doing machine learning in 2009
as an engineer and back uh back when we
were just building single task models
and doing uh kind of more traditional
machine learning um it felt like there
were a lot of nuts and bolts that had to
be considered. Um now it feels like the
the game has changed quite a bit. So so
tell us how how you've experienced ML
Ops to change over the last couple of
years.
Yes, I also started doing machine
learning around that time, around 2010.
And I do remember in those early days
the model development was rather manual
with deployments being ad hoc. We
probably all remember you just started
uh back in the days like me uh sharing
data and models with a USB. Obviously,
this approach lacked scalability,
reliability, and the collaboration was
rather bumpy, right? If we just think
how the field of ML Ops has matured, we
started to incorporate and extend the
principles from DevOps to automate the
building, testing, and deployment of
both data and model assets, right? Um
this was very necessary because the
dynamic nature of machine learning where
the data changes and model requires
continuous monitoring and retraining.
Well, I mean, over the time, probably
like late 2010s, um a wide tool of
ecosystem uh for ML Ops arose.
And then we were able to manage the
entire ML life cycle. Also, the rise of
the cloud was very important to further
accelerate the adoption and of automated
pipelines and also serverless machine
learning.
This actually helped us a lot to to
increase the scalability, the
reliability, while decreasing also costs
for production and and experimentation.
Now, more recently, with the rise of
generative AI, it has pushed again uh ML
Ops to adapt. Uh
I think now we are incorporating new
roles like prompt engineers, AI
engineers. We have a broader artifact
management including model
configurations, foundation models to
use, prompt templates, chaining
pipelines, etc.
And also a shift towards uh holistic
application monitoring. Before we were
focusing only on the model, on the
machine learning monitoring mon-
monitoring the machine learning model,
sorry, but now we are focusing on
monitoring the entire end-to-end
application. Uh we're also thinking
about end-to-end passing user feedback
and doing task specific and custom
evaluations of the entire system and of
the singular single uh individual parts.
Moreover, you all know uh we have new
models and new frameworks arising every
day, so it also demands exceptionally
agile workflows.
Um I love that you called out the the
broad spectrum of artifact management
that teams have to deal with today both
in terms of, you know, doing things like
defining functions, but then also
monitoring prompts, um how prompts
change over time, the the chaining
templates. Um it's really really
fascinating to see how some things have
gotten a lot easier, um but a lot of
other things have gotten much more
challenging to manage. So I love uh I
love that detail and and also really
really excited to see somebody else
who's like one of the OGs of machine
learning um that is that is still like
interested in this new brave generative
AI world. Um awesome.
Um next question um for Anant and for
Olivia, uh tell me about the importance
of evaluation for productionizing
models. Is it only possible for text or
is multimodal evaluation also an option?
Um and Olivia, I know you're leading one
of our Evals teams over at Google
DeepMind, so welcome. Really excited to
have you here.
Cool. Thank you, Paige. And yes, uh I
think I'll briefly start off by
mentioning evaluation since this topic
was brought up quite a a lot in the last
days and questions in Discord as well
and I know I got a lot of you okay, come
to day five, so uh hopefully you had a
chance to read through the white
evaluation part of the white paper, uh
but evaluation has a lot of dimensions
to it. Um I'll start off with mentioning
some parts of text evaluation and Olivia
will dive deeper into multimodal and um
uh the structured the
disassembly of various tasks for
evaluation.
So, um evaluation uh depends long story
short for text evaluation, uh it's um
it's incredi- incredible uh part of uh
ML Ops. You cannot have just like how it
was a predictive AI as Gabriella
mentioned, uh you still need to
evaluate. However, evaluating a
generated image or string value, right,
a response is very task specific and it
becomes far more complex. It's not just
a singular value that you can kind of
calculate numerical value and calculate
accuracy on anymore. It's far more task
specific and nuanced. So, uh on the text
evaluation side of things, um we have um
we can use this the traditional
techniques which kind of compare like um
things that are document or sentence
level where uh using computational
metrics, let's say BLEU or ROUGE scores
where you kind of compare the generated
sentence, but given that you have an
existing ground truth or an existing
golden human like uh thing to compare
to, so it only exists as okay, how much
how good is the
generated answer compared to the golden
answer which I was expecting it to So,
um the the and so you the some uh so it
can be used for machine translation and
many other tasks. The problem with this
approach is that um it's comparing to
one go ground truth answer, so you need
a ground truth answer. And secondly,
several tasks like summarization and
very task specific one specific answers
are very hard to compare um as a unigram
or n-gram basically token basis
subsequence of the strings and compare
with an ex- one existing answer because
there's many ways to write a summary
which might all be correct or even
better, but it's really hard to judge
that by solely comparing it with an
existing reference point.
Now, there is where
LLM as a judge or auterator based
systems uh come into play. And um for
text, this is also very important
because you can uh either take an LLM
where uh to judge another LLM's response
and say okay, let's say you had a
prompt, you got a response from an LLM,
you can have another LLM which is kind
of um specialized at evaluation judge it
on a say on a scale of one to five and
uh how good is this response compared to
what I like given the prompt and
instructions and and explain why. So,
this is kind of like you can uh judge it
as or sometimes um you can have uh they
can be a tie and and two responses can
be very similar or generated from
different models or settings and you
would like to compare side-by-side
comparison which is how humans evaluate
things. It's like take two responses to
a prompt and say which one of these two
are better because humans when given a
bunch of responses
do not tend to look at all the responses
at once. So, they they tend to kind of
compare in pairs. And this is where
side-by-side evaluation is also possible
while you compare pairs um uh responses
at once. And yeah, there's a lot of um
ways you can do that. You have uh
services uh like Vertex AI which offer
an evaluation service, but also as you
mentioned earlier, Paige, Prompt Foo and
other uh
um open source alternatives to it as
well. So, Olivia uh has worked on a lot
of great multimodal evaluation and other
techniques, so I'll hand it over to you,
Olivia, for diving more deep into that.
Thanks, Anant. Um Yeah, so hi. I'm a
researcher at Google DeepMind and I've
been working evaluation space and in
particular in the multimodal space.
Um and just to kind of add to what Anant
said, I think evaluation is a really key
area in ML,
but it's actually become a really
interesting So, it's been an interesting
research direction, but it's become even
more interesting with these large models
that are just being used in such a wide
variety of settings and for different
capabilities. And it's become really
difficult to even think about the
evaluation problem and how to break it
down. Um it's something that I've been
thinking about for quite a while.
Um and in particular, kind of this first
thing that I tend to think about is what
use cases do you really imagine your
model being used for?
And can we then build like an evaluation
data set that has uh coverage over these
kinds of use cases?
And I think it's really key to think
about building this data set as it's
going to be what you're going to be
evaluating your metric and your models
on. So, if it doesn't have good coverage
and if it's not really covering the
things that you care about, then you're
not really going to know how your model
is doing and you're not going to be able
to monitor how it changes over time.
Um and so maybe it's not the most
exciting part of the process, but it's a
really key and fundamental part of the
process.
Um and so kind of what once you know
what you want to evaluate and you have
sufficient coverage and sufficient
confidence,
um then it's time to actually build your
evaluator.
And Anant did a really great job of
talking about the different ways for
text, but I think multimodal is
particularly interesting as you have,
you know, image input and text input,
and you're not evaluating them in
isolation, but you want to evaluate um
the their combination.
And I've been looking mostly at image
generation and video generation, which
is particularly interesting as there's
there was never a notion of kind of a
ground truth. We never There's never a
ground truth image that can be generated
from a given caption. And so,
historically, it wasn't very easy to
evaluate these models, and people relied
on simple things like CLIP or FID, even
though as models became better even
maybe 2 or 3 years ago, people knew that
these weren't fit for purpose.
And one interesting thing that we've
been looking at in our Gecko work is how
we can actually leverage Gemini models
as black black boxes and see whether
they're like effective for this kind of
task.
And we particularly looked at alignment.
So, we were looking at, you know, if I
have a prompt and I generate an image,
then is that image aligned with prompt?
So, for example, I want to generate an
image of a dog wearing a top hat. Is the
image generated? Does that actually have
a dog? Is the dog actually wearing a top
hat? Et cetera. Are the properties in
the prompt actually in the generated
images?
And we could follow an auditor type
approach, which is um
potentially very useful for many
scenarios, but we wanted to get away
from just generating a single score and
think about how we could give the user
more control and um understanding what
the metric is doing. And so, what we did
was we thought about how can we use a
Gemini model to break down this task
into subquestions. So, for the prompt I
was saying, you know, is there dog? Is
there a top hat? And then given these
questions, we can ask the Gemini model
to answer the question given the image,
and then if there is no there's no dog,
then the answer would be no.
And then what we can do is that we when
we give this final metric, we can also
give this uh breakdown to the user, and
then the user can actually see, you
know, where is the where is our model
doing badly?
And then we can give the user a kind of
intuition and an ability to have some
flexibility with the metric. They can
add questions or remove questions or
evaluate for additional properties.
And I think this is like really quite an
exciting approach that we found to be
quite effective um to compare models and
also multiple generations for a single
prompt. It's also quite general, so
we're thinking about how we can
generalize it to other modalities or
combinations thereof. And we're excited
to see where it goes and how it can be
useful. And I just want to finish by
saying like that while this is one
direction of work, I do think that
there's a lot of interesting uh work
that's been happening in the space more
generally both from Google and
externally. And I'm excited to see how
we can use in multimodal kind of the
work that's been doing in text in order
to push it.
Absolutely, and we can definitely add a
link to your research um particularly
Gecko um uh as well as some of the other
really uh exciting multimodal evals that
DeepMind has been creating uh in the
video description. Um I love your uh
your calling out that you can use Gemini
almost as like an auditor to help uh to
help with some of the multimodal evals.
Um and I saw another uh a blog post just
recently posted too around video
understanding. I think it was the
Neptune
um the Neptune eval that would be it
would be interesting to call out too.
So, uh
so I love uh I love this brave new world
of being able to to do multimodal evals
um including image generation and video
generation evals and using models to to
kind of help with those tasks. It's
amazing. Um so, thank you thank you for
that great overview and uh and also for
pointing out that um evals are only as
good as how well you specify your
problem um and how well you you kind of
architect your eval to ensure that you
have coverage over the thing that you
care about and the thing that you want
to be measuring. Um it's super
important, and I don't think enough
people spend uh spend time thinking
about it. Um so, it's great to to
reinforce this in the in the educational
content.
Cool.
Um next question um for Socrates, um
what ML ops challenges are no longer
priorities given that many companies are
now using REST API calls as opposed to
training, deploying, and maintaining
their own models. We talked a little bit
about this already um with Gabriella, I
think, but what has been your
perspective on um on what things are are
a little bit easier now
um given that most companies are are
calling models as REST APIs?
Sure. Calling a model like a a REST API
means like somebody else has done the
heavy lifting for for us, right? That
means that someone else has prepared a
massive amount of data to train a model,
evaluate the model by checking a loss
function and how close is to the results
that we need to have. Uh someone else
has passed through all the different
steps of auditing what data and
artifacts we used to produce a model.
So, all this will disappear by calling a
model like a a REST API. Of course,
uh the customers or everyone who is
using the the foundation models can jump
directly on building an application an
application. That means that they don't
really need to have data science skills
extensively except if they start
fine-tuning a model.
Uh
of course, uh having prompt engineers,
AI engineers that are the new skills, we
need a little bit to see how we can move
the data science and ML engineers to
that space, but uh I think if they are
experts in their domain and the
applications they want to build, this is
relatively easy.
Now, as you can imagine, the classic
approach that we had was data
preparation, training, evaluation, et
cetera, a very long process. Now, we
start directly with evaluation, and this
is a big benefit. Why? Because we can
reduce massively the amount of time to
build our application. Of course, in the
evaluation, we have uh new parameters as
Anant said earlier, right? We cannot
rely on uh how the loss function
performs, but we need to rely on
toxicity, factual knowledge, and other
more task-specific metrics.
The next one is about monitoring. Now,
we don't need to have all these data or
model drift classic ways of thinking
about. We need to have more about how
our model drifts in terms of toxicity or
factual knowledge or other task-specific
metrics that we have.
And lastly is about guardrails, right?
Uh what I want to say is in classic
machine learning, we used to to have
specific guardrails about the specific
uh number limits, if I may say, or
thresholds. Now, we need to be closer to
the understanding of the use case and to
set more limits or more guardrails
around uh
a specific topic that we are examining.
Awesome. I love uh calling out all of
the new things that we need to learn and
and to kind of be uh considered and
thoughtful about and how user-focused
all of those things um all of those
things are. Um so, thank you for thank
you for um pointing out things like
toxic toxicity
uh and then the other the other
components of model deployments that um
are are really really kind of
mission-critical important to get right.
Um uh and the that we're building tools
to help users um figure out how to
wrangle. About the model deployment that
you mentioned that I forgot to to to
point out, right? Yep. In classic
machine learning, also someone needs to
be responsible to deploy the model and
ensure auto-scaling mechanisms that then
point is up and running continuously.
Now, we don't have this concern, right?
Somebody else has deployed that and
makes sure that the model is available
for everyone. Thank you for this. Yep.
Yep, the auto-scaling auto-scaling is
something that Google cares very very
deeply about, and so just for my
personal projects, I really really love
that I don't have to to worry about
deploying an open-source model on some
sort of server myself um and that I can
just rely on all right, well, if I I get
a lot more kind of people using my
system, um then it will gracefully scale
along with the number of user requests
as opposed to me having to figure out
how to do that balancing.
Um
cool.
Awesome. So, next next question. Um this
is the perfect segue into Vertex AI um
and to uh to to kind of Cloud AI's
offerings. Um Advait, welcome. Um tell
us a little bit about Vertex AI and
about why a customer might want to use
it at their company.
Yeah, great. Uh hey everyone, Advait
Parkar. I'm one of the product managers
for Vertex AI, and Vertex is an
enterprise AI platform that's meant to
be kind of like your one-stop shop for
everything when it comes to machine
learning. So, that means both generative
as well as non-generative type tasks
that an ML team at a company might want
to do. So, if you need access to the API
for Gemini, but also other models like
models from Anthropic or from Llama uh
Meta's Llama models or Mistral models,
you can get access to all those models
and then start to think about how are
you going to ground those models, use
them for generative applications, or
building out agents. Um and around this,
you need a whole set of tools around ML
ops, a lot of the the topic of of today.
Uh but the same concept still also apply
in non-generative use cases. So, if you
want to still build a time series model
or anything that is non-generative in
nature, you can still use Vertex AI for
all your needs. Um now, depending on
where you are in your skill set and your
journey inside of machine learning, you
can either build everything by hand by
having managed notebook environments,
managed compute to train your models,
experiment tracking, ML ops pipelines
that you don't have to run that actual
underlying Kubernetes clusters uh for,
or you can take uh a simpler approach by
using something like AutoML. For AutoML,
it's a point-and-click interface. You
don't necessarily need to know that much
about machine learning, but understand
how to evaluate the quality of those
models and provide the right quality
high-quality data.
So, it starts to abstract away a lot of
the effort that you would have done by
managing a lot of the infrastructure.
You don't want to necessarily be a
DevOps engineer, perhaps you prefer to
focus on ML.
Um and and you can start to tackle
various challenges, whether they be
generative or not.
Yeah, that's a great overview. You know,
we've been talking a lot about um kind
of open source libraries and and kind of
things that you can stand up yourself
and and kind of run on on commodity
hardware infrastructure. Um but there
can be uh immense value and time saving
and and kind of uh bundling it all
together and then having managed
services for all of those systems as
opposed to trying to maintain and
upgrade and modify all of those the
products yourself. Um so really love
that overview of Vertex is trying to
help people focus on uh the value add,
focus on machine learning or or uh kind
of the impact to their business as
opposed to to trying to figure out how
to wrangle all of the services um and
deploy them themselves.
Um awesome. Next question for Veer, um
what specific ML Ops practices should be
prioritized when starting with
generative AI? Um and how do these
differ from traditional ML Ops
workflows?
Um and are there any beginner-friendly
tools that help to uh help to kind of
manage these practices for foundation
models on Vertex?
A great question. So
I'll actually build upon what Socrates
and Advaita left. So
in the world of predictive AI, the
models are typically self-contained and
trained for specific tasks, right? I
mean, in the world of generative AI on
the other other hand
models and particularly LLMs, um they
are more versatile. They require a
prompt to guide their behavior and
output. So this difference, uh it
necessitates
considering the prompted model component
as the fundamental unit of gen AI ML
Ops. So with and this encap- encompasses
both uh model and the prompt.
So coming to the question, so which ML
Ops practices to uh to prioritize when
starting with gen AI on Vertex AI
specifically, right?
First is think about model discovery.
Efficiently identifying the optimal
foundation models for your use case from
a vast landscape of options is crucial.
So this entails a systematic approach to
evaluating various models based on
factors like quality or latency, uh
development time, cost, and compliance.
So we have to evaluate yourself on
factors. So that's the first step. Uh
second, think about prompt engineering.
This is iterative process involves
crafting and refining prompts
to elicit the desired outputs for the
model. It's crucial to manage prompts as
both
data as well as code.
Um utilizing the data-centric practices
like validation, drift detection,
code-centric practices like version
control and testing. So it's not just
first time, it's like how you how you go
back and fine-tune the prompts
themselves also.
Third, think about chaining and
augmentation, right? As LLMs can
struggle with recency and hallucinations
chaining multiple models together and
integrating
external APIs and data sources is very
essential. So uh
now uh
I'll I'll also touch upon the tooling
that Vertex AI offers in this space.
Like
we have we offer tools like grounding
extensions. We have vector search, agent
builder to support these kind of needs.
Next is uh model tuning and training. In
this context, Vertex AI provides robust
platform for fine-tuning LLMs,
supporting techniques like supervised
fine-tuning, reinforcement learning with
human feedback and distillation.
Managing the artifacts, measuring the
impact of the tuning, and leveraging
tools like
uh Vertex AI's model registry
and
other tools that actually support within
the Google Cloud like Data Plex are
essential for this process.
Uh
as we think about data, right? Think
about data practices as well. So
generative AI applications leverage
various data types from different data
sources. So implementing traditional ML
Ops and
uh DevOps practices is like vital to
ensure this re- reproducibility,
adaptability,
uh governance
and continuous improvement across all
data types involved.
Next is evaluation and uh
others have covered a lot on this topic.
I'll just quickly talk about it.
Evaluating generative AI models requires
both manual and automatic automated
approaches, right? Uh custom evaluation
methods and metrics are often necessary
to
This is due to the complexity and
subjectivity of this model outputs.
So addressing adversarial attacks is
also crucial. Vertex AI provides
tools like that we already discussed
about, but these are automated metrics.
Again, coming to automation, automatic
side-to-side comparison
to evaluate different models and uh
rapid evaluation API to support this
kind of a process.
Next is
uh in terms of ML Ops, now we are
thinking about deployment. So deploying
generative AI systems involves managing
various components often like using
standard software engineering practices
like version control, CI/CD. So in in
this space, Vertex AI offers endpoints
for deploying models and features like
citation checkers
safety scores
watermarking,
uh content moderation tools. But in
addition, if you think about the bigger
Google Cloud, we also have tools like
Cloud Build, Cloud Deploy for CI/CD.
Some of these were actually part of the
uh of the yes demo
earlier.
Um next, once the
once it is deployed into
uh production, now we are thinking about
governance. This is where establishing
control, accountability transparency
over entire development and
deployments life cycle is all critical.
So this involves governing the chain
element life cycle um
uh data, tuned models, and code. All
everything that we have covered so far
needs to be governed.
Tools like Vertex AI Feature Store Model
Registry and Data Plex play significant
roles in this aspect.
So I think I covered
overall ML Ops process that applies to
gen AI
uh on how
how that changes, as well as I touched
upon a bunch of tools. But to summarize
the tools for the beginner-friendly
tools is what being is being asked in
this question. I'd say start with Vertex
AI Model Garden, which is where you'll
pick up the model of your choice.
Next
uh for beginners, Vertex AI Studio is
extremely helpful because it features a
playground where you can expand
experiment with different prompts and
models and making it ideal for uh the
beginner-friendly environment. Uh
eventually, you'll also get into agent
builders. I mean, this is a place where
you can
build your own agents, generative AI
agents, like conversational chatbots,
things like that. And then uh for the ML
Ops itself, we have Vertex AI Pipelines.
So yeah, we'll stop there.
Awesome. Thank you so much. Um and I I
definitely
I definitely think that there are there
are many different products that are
available on Vertex AI um for folks to
take a look at. Um what are some
strategies uh Gabriella um to monitor
large generative AI models um in Google
Cloud and production environments with
high variability in user queries? Um
would love to learn more about this.
Yeah, when we think about monitoring
generative AI models, especially those
ones with high variability in user
queries, we need to track two things. Uh
from one side, we need to track the
system performance. Um by system
performance, I mean the latency, how
fast are the responses, um the query
size, how big are the queries, and these
other aspects. The other part is to also
uh track the the model quality itself,
like are the answers accurate, relevant,
safe, etc.
Like the most reliable way to achieve
this is de- like having detailed logs of
everything that happens.
Including like user queries, retrieve
snippets, uh prompts, generated answers,
user feedback, latencies, etc.
So one thing we can do is to store all
of this data in Google Cloud um
BigQuery, which is a fully managed and
serverless data warehouse.
Why BigQuery is because it is like a
cost-effective way to keep uh this data,
analyze it, and create dashboards to
visualize the performance and identify
um areas of improvement, um etc. Like
just to give a concrete example for the
case that you are presenting here, it's
like once your data is in BigQuery, you
can create embeddings for the user
queries and model answers, and then
group similar ones together. You can
analyze then the user feedback for a
specific cluster of queries, um and then
BigQuery also works very well or
integrates with other tools like Looker
which will enable to to build a
dashboard for monitoring, and it will
give us like a clear aggregated view of
both the system and model performance,
including metrics and feedback for a
specific um query of clusters.
Another thing we can aggregate here is
like you can also leverage open source
tools for observability, and then couple
them with Google Cloud Trace and Google
Cloud Login in a way that you can
instrument every answer given by the uh
generative AI model and you will also
have a detailed tracing. Um actually,
this information that I'm saying was
also presented or is part of the demo
that
earlier presented earlier.
Yeah. I love I love BigQuery as an
option to store logs and prompts and
data about model interactions,
especially given how many wonderful kind
of integrations BigQuery has introduced
with things like Looker
and also sheets and then even the
machine learning features that have been
added into BigQuery.
I really love being able to use Gemini
to help me write SQL queries to interact
with with BigQuery a little bit more
effectively. So I love that answer. Um
and if folks haven't experimented with
BigQuery, there are a lot of there are a
lot of great resources to get started.
We can add some in the YouTube video
comments as well.
Um
Excellent. Next and final question.
For Socrates and for Advait, how does
Vertex AI enhance ML Ops for
foundational models and generative AI
applications? Are there specific
features that make it more suitable for
generative AI
compared to other tools or platforms?
And we've covered some of these already
but would love to get your perspective.
Yeah, absolutely.
If you think about it, a lot of the same
concepts that applied with ML Ops in the
past still translate when it comes to
generative applications. Um so if you
start with let's say something like
prompt engineering, conceptually it's
actually kind of similar to let's say if
you're doing hyperparameter tuning. It's
something where you in the past would
have manually done it. You would have to
tweak it to see how you get the best
performance.
Today you don't have to necessarily do
that.
Inside of Vertex AI, we have our prompt
optimization tool. So you bring in a
data set and eval data set and it will
do the optimizations of your prompts on
your behalf, simplifying and removing a
lot of the art of prompt optimization
and making it a little bit more
statistically driven in nature.
Beyond that, everyone's spoken a lot
about evals. I also share the belief
that evals are kind of the key thing
that you need to land to get
high-quality results.
So inside of Vertex AI, you can do
evaluations both to compare models, to
compare prompts, to see how your various
different parameters that you select
impact your results and also see how
fine-tuning impacts your your model
quality.
Um and then finally, there's a lot of
thought around well once you're in
production, how do you actually monitor
the performance of this model? This is a
bit more of an emerging space
specifically for generative AI,
but we're rolling out an experimental
capability to
evaluate and monitor models in
production to see what topics are
starting to happen.
Are they adhering to safety protocols
that you've defined from your safety
filters and how can you make changes to
the performance of the models by going
back to those prior steps and augmenting
your prompts or doing things like
fine-tuning, which you can do all
directly inside of Vertex.
And to add to Advait, right?
Of course we have some other toys in GCP
that can help everyone to industrialize
generative AI applications. For example,
you can combine the Vertex AI valve
components that Advait mentioned with
pipelines and experiments and to create
a
a quite scalable experimentation
environment for GenAI. Or we have prompt
management
prompt management that helps us a lot to
store our prompts, understand what went
wrong, reuse them, or try and change
change them after evaluation. And then
we have a prompt gallery that helps us a
lot in order to start with a a nice
version of a prompt for a particular
application.
Um awesome. I love the kind of the the
end-to-end solutions that are that are
offered on on Google Cloud and then also
how many of them are built to scale
effectively
as the number of users grow for
enterprises and for companies. I think
that's that's kind of mission-critical
important and something that is
underappreciated until companies do need
to scale.
So it's it's great to hear great to hear
those options.
Um and then next, thank you all so much
for for being wonderful kind of expert
hosts and guests and and giving great
Q&A as well as overviews of code labs.
Really appreciate you taking the time to
come here and to help share your
knowledge with all of our students and
all of the people who are dialed in to
this generative AI intensive course. So
virtual round of applause
for for all of our guest presenters
and
and if folks want to learn more about
them, their work, please refer to the
white papers as well as the links that
we have in the YouTube video. Um so
thank you again and now we're going to
head into our last and final section for
today,
the pop quiz.
All right, everyone get out your pens,
your pencils, your paper and start
getting ready to take notes. This is our
last and final pop quiz for the
generative AI intensive course all about
machine learning,
generative AI Ops and how to deploy
these systems into production. So with
that, I am going to go ahead and get
started. Question number one, which of
these is not a core practice of ML Ops
for generative AI applications as
discussed in the white paper. So
hopefully you are paying attention
during today's readings. Is it prompt
engineering and evaluation as an
iterative cycle? Is it data validation,
model evaluation, and model monitoring?
Is it training a foundational model from
scratch or is it managing and versioning
prompt templates, chain definitions, and
external data sets? We also touched on
this little bit in the Q&A section with
Gabriella. Which of these is not a core
practice of ML Ops for generative AI
applications?
Um
I'm going to give you five,
four,
three,
two, one.
The answer is C. Training a foundational
model from scratch is not part of ML
Ops. You know, after you're doing these
ML Ops for generative AI applications,
the model has already been built
and you're just concerned with deploying
it in a robust and production-friendly
way. Um so question number two, what is
a prompt template in the context of
generative AI? Is it a simple text input
from the user? Is it a set of
instructions and examples with
placeholders for user input? Is it the
foundational model itself or is it the
final output generated by the model?
Which of these is a prompt template? Um
I'm going to give you five,
four,
three,
two,
one.
Hopefully everybody got the answer
correct, which is B. A set of
instructions and examples with
placeholders for user inputs. Those are
prompt templates.
And as you deploy these models into
production, you're going to have to
worry about version controlling all of
your great prompt templates.
Um question number three, what is the
purpose of chaining in generative AI
applications? Um is it to maintain
recency in the model's outputs? Is it to
avoid hallucination and maintain recency
in the model's outputs? Is it to
increase the complexity of the model or
is it to D reduce the efficiency of the
model? Think back to your white papers,
your readings, and also those great
podcasts. What is the purpose of
chaining in generative AI applications?
I'm going to give you five,
four,
three,
two,
one. The answer is B, to avoid
hallucination and maintain recency in
the model's outputs. You know, as you
chain together all of the responses,
the model's kind of understand which
information it should be using in order
to guide further outputs. Um so
hopefully everybody was paying attention
and has been getting all of these
questions right. Um number four, why is
evaluation a crucial step in the
development of generative AI systems?
Think back to the discussion with Olivia
and Anant. Um is it to ensure the model
is deployed to the correct
infrastructure? Is it to optimize
resource utilization and reduce latency?
Is it to track the lineage of data and
model versions? Or is it to D measure
the quality and effectiveness of the
model's outputs? Why are evals a crucial
step in the development of generative AI
systems?
Hopefully everybody's thinking about
this very hard.
And the correct answer is
it is D, to measure the quality and
effectiveness of the model's outputs.
And evals can be not just text-based but
also multimodal, so encompassing video,
images, audio, text, code, all of the
above.
Question number five, which Vertex AI
product allows for recurrent execution
of evaluation jobs in production skew
and drift detection processes? Is it
Vertex AI model monitoring?
Vertex AI pipelines, Vertex AI feature
store, or Vertex AI model registry?
Which of these allows for recurrent
execution of evaluation jobs?
The answer is B, Vertex AI pipelines.
And this was our last question of the of
the course of the five-day generative AI
intensive practice
and also for today. I also wanted to say
thank you so much for for tuning in, for
learning, for sharing your knowledge
with others, and for also asking all of
these wonderful and great questions. We
have really enjoyed getting to to
kind of work with you, to be with you,
to be part of this beautiful community
over the course of the last five days.
And appreciate you taking the time
to to kind of work with us to understand
and to to come up to speed with all of
these really interesting new tools
and to start brainstorming how they
could be applicable to your work
and to the applications that you're
building.
So again just from the the bottom of all
of our hearts from our host from our
guest presenters from the from the folks
who have been working so hard on all of
these white papers. We appreciate you.
We appreciate you taking the time
and are really truly excited to see what
you build. Hopefully this is just the
first installment
and there will be many more of these to
come. But
it's been great to to get to know you
and have a wonderful rest of the year
rest of the month.
Bye.